A Finding Aid to the John Evans Papers, 1957-2012, bulk 1970s-2012, in the Archives of American Art AAA.evanjohn
Archives of American Art
John Evans papers
bulk 1970-2012
1957-2012
AAA.evanjohn
Archives of American Art
7.1 Linear feet
The papers of John Evans, 1957-2012, bulk 1970s-2000, measure 7.1 linear feet and document the collage artist's involvement with mail art. The vast majority of letters are from mail artists, often with embellished envelopes. Writings are a thesis about mail art by Marya Trianfellos. Subject files concern art stamps, mail art shows and events, Ray Johnson's death and memorial tributes to him. The most thoroughly documented mail art project, "John Evans Fake Collages," is of unknown origin. In addition, there are a few items relating to projects conceived by Evans and more substantial documentation of projects initiated by Christina Behmenburg, Leslie Caldera, Ryosuke Cohen, Peter W. Kaufmann, Angela and Peter Netmail.
Evans, John
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Margaret Evans, widow of John Evans, in 2013.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of John Evans, 1957-2012, bulk 1970s-2000, measure 7.1 linear feet and document the collage artist's involvement with mail art. The vast majority of letters - many with embelllished envelopes - are from mail artists. Writings include a thesis about mail art by Marya Trianfellos. Subject files concern art stamps, Ray Johnson's death and subsequent memorial tributes, mail art shows and other events. The most thoroughly documented mail art project, "John Evans Fake Collages," is of unknown origin. In addition, there are a few items relating to projects conceived by Evans, and more substantial documentation of projects initiated by Christina Behmenburg, Leslie Caldera, Ryosuke Cohen, Peter W. Kaufmann, Angela and Peter Netmail.
Evans's mail art correspondents include: Dr. Al Ackerman (Blaster), Anna Banana (Banana Productions), Roy Arenella, Guy Bleus (The Administration Centre 42.292), buZ blurr, Richard C., Leslie Caldera (Creative Thing), Carl T. Chew, Buster Cleveland, Ryosuke Cohen, Chuck Welch (Cracker Jack Kid), Robin Crozier, Jerome D'Angelo, Irene Dogmatic (Dogmmystique/Dogmatique Misticky), Morris David Dorenfeld, Jerry Dreva, Donald Evans, James Evans, Walt Evans, Fa Ga Ga Ga, A. M. Fine, Bill Gaglione (Picasso Gaglione), John Held, Jr., HICO, E. F. Higgins, III, Rudd Janssen, Dianne Jenkins, Ray Johnson, Tod Jorgenssen, Chester Kasnowski, On Kawara, Gene Laughter, Michael Leigh (A.1. Waste Paper Co., Ltd.), David M. Miller, Minoy, Mohammed, Robert Morilla, Art Nahpro (Paul Jackson), Carlo Pittore, E. M. Plunkett, Steve Random, Robert Rocola, Marilyn K. Rosenberg, Andreas Senser, Skooter, Smegma (Scarlatina Lust, Alex Torrid Zone Igloo, Pardon My Myrth, Alexander Josef Hirka), D. C. spaulding, Lon Spiegelman, John Tostada (Tostdada, Oh Boy Mailart!), Pat Tavenner (Mail Queen), Third Story, Benedict J. Tisa, Sonja Van der Burg (Afzed), Whitson (Peter Whitson Warren), and Robert Warren.
Arrangement note
The collectionis arranged as 4 series:
Series 1: Letters, 1957-2012 (Boxes 1-6, OV 8; 5.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Writings, 1983-1991 (Box 6; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1970s-2012 (Boxes 6-7; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Mail Art Projects, 1986-2012 (Box 7, OV 8; 0.8 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
John Evans (1932-2012), a collage artist in New York City, was an active participant in mail art.
After attending the Art Institute of Chicago, Evans moved to New York in 1963. He was a member of the Neo-Dada community and interested in Fluxus events. Meeting Ray Johnson and a few other mail artists at a party introduced Evans to mail art and led to many long term friendships.
Between 1964 and 2000, Evans produced a daily collage of found objects collected from the street, pasted onto a sketchbook page, enhanced with watercolor, and stamped with the date. Each collage included the image of a duck's head known as "Ursuline Duck," a reference to his friend Ursule Molinaro (1914-2000). The collages were, in effect, a diary that recorded everyday life and referenced his exhibition activities. John Evans: Collages, a monograph published in 2004, reproduced 364 collages representative of his style over time. His largest mail art project, "Fake John Evans Collages," spanned several years and was in progress at the time of his death.
John Evans died on October 5, 2012 following a heart attack.
Arenella, Roy; Banana, Anna, 1940-; Behmenburg, Christa; Blaster, Al; Bleus, Guy; Caldera, Leslie; Chew, C. T., (Carl T.), 1948-; Cleveland, Buster, -1998; Cohen, Ryosuke, 1948-; Crozier, Robin; D'Angelo, Jerome, D.; Dorenfeld, Morris David; Dreva, Jerry; Evans, Donald; Evans, James; Evans, Walt; Gaglione, Bill; Held, John; Higgins, E. F., 1949-; Janssen, Ruud, 1959-; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Jorgenssen, Tod; Kasnowski, Chester; Kaufmann, Peter W.; Kawara, K. Japanese; Küstermann, Peter, 1950-; Leigh, Michael; Miller, David M.; Morilla, Robert; Pittore, Carlo; Plunkett, Ed, 1922-; Random, S., (Steven), 1954-; Rocola, Robert; Rosenberg, Marilyn K.; Senser, Andreas, 1942-1989; Spiegelman, Lon; Tavenner, Pat; Tisa, Benedict J.; Tostada, John; Trianfellos, Marya; Von der Burg, Sonja; Warren, Robert Penn, 1905-; Collage; Illustrated letters; Mail art
- Letters, 1957-2012; Series 1; 5.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-6, OV 8
  Scope and Contents note
  Most letters are from other mail artists. Many are about correspondence art and the artists' careers. Letters from some artists who became close friends focus on personal and family news. Other letters contain invitations to exchange work, exhibit, or participate in mail art projects. Enclosures are frequent and include found objects, a wide variety of printed materials, and a few small artifacts.
  Arrangement note
  Letters are alphabetized by name of sender. Miscellaneous files for each letter of the alphabet contain letters from correspondents represented by fewer than 5 letters; within each folder, material is in rough alphabetical order.
  Throughout this series, envelopes precede their contents and the address sides of post cards and aerograms face upward. Letters without envelopes, empty envelopes, and separated enclosures are placed at the ends of folders. Researchers must take care to maintain the order and should notify reference staff if the arrangement appears to have been disturbed.
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1980s-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ackerman, Dr. Al/Blaster, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Andre, Michael, 1990s-2009 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anna Banana/Banana Productions, 1990s-2011 (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
  - Arenella, Roy, 1990s-2003 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - B, Miscellaneous, undated; 1965-2012 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bleus, Guy/The Adminstration Centre 42.292, 1970s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - buZ blurr, 1980s-2012 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1975-2008 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Richard C., 1970s-2012 (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
  - Caldera, Leslie/Creative Thing, 1975-2012 (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Caldera, Leslie/Creative Thing, 1975-2012 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Chew, Carl T., 2011-2012 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cleveland, Buster, 1980s-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cohen, Ryosuke, 1980s-2012 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cracker Jack Kid/Chuck Welch, 1990-2012 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Crozier, Robin, 1975-1980s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1962-2012 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - D'Angelo, Jerome, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Irene Dogmatic/Dogmystique/Dogmatique Mysticky, 1975-1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Dorenfeld, Morris David, 1993-2000s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dreva, Jimmy, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - E, Miscellaneous, 1980s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Evans, Donald, 1971-2003 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Evans, James, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Evans, Walt, 1980s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 2000s-2010s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fa Ga Ga Ga, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Ferguson, Frank, 1980s-2010s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fine, A. M., 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gaglione, Bill/Picasso Gaglioni, 1990s-2012 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Held, John, Jr., 1980s-2012 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    includes 1 CD
  - HICO, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Higgins, E. F., III, 1970s-2012 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - I, Miscellaneous, 1970s-2012 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1979-1980s; undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - James, Inex, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Janssen, Rudd, 1990s-2012 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jenkins, Dianne, undated; 1980s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Johnson, Ray, 1960s-1995 (Box 3, Folder 18-22)
  - Jorgensen, Tod, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Kasnowski, Chester, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Kawara, On, 1983-2006 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - L, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Laughter, Gene, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Leigh, Michael/A.1. Waste Paper Co., Ltd., 1980-2012 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - Lionelli, D., 1957-1965 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1972-2012 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Massa, Jacques, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Miller, David M., 1983-1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Minoy, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mohammed, 1970s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Morillo, Robert, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - N, Miscellaneous, 1970s-2012; undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Naphro, Art/Paul Jackson, 1980s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
  - O, Miscellaneous, 1993-2012; undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Olson, Richard, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1980s-2012; undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Phillips, Stephen, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Pittore, Carlo, 1980s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
  - Plunkett, E. M., 1970s-2012 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - R, Miscellaneous, 1980s-1990s; undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Random, Steve, 1980s-2000s (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - Rocola, Robert, 1984-1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rosenberg, Marilyn R., 1980-2001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - S, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Senser, Andreas, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Skooter, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Smegma/Scarlatina Lust/Alex Torrid Zone Igloo/Pardon My Myrth/Alexander Josef Hirka, undated; 2000s (Box 5, Folder 7-9)
  - Spaulding, D. C., 2000s; undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Spiegelman, Lou, 1978-2001; Oversized material housed in OV 8 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - T, Miscellaneous, 1978-2005 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Tavenner, Pat/Mail Queen, 1973-1983; undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Third Story, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Tisa, Benedict J., 1980s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Tostada, John/Tostdada/Oh Boy Mailart!, 1990s-2012 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - U, Miscellaneous, 1996-2008 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - V, Miscellaneous, 1965-1990s (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Van der Burg, Sonja/Afzed, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1987-2012 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Warner, Robert, 1980s-2005 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Whitson/Peter Whitson Warren, 1975-2000s (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - X-Z, Miscellaneous, 1983-2010 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Letter from Box 5, Folder 11, 1984 (Box OV 8)
- Writings, 1983-1991; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Box 6
  Writings by Evans include a book review of Correspondence Art by Michael Crane, circa 1984. A brief essay, "Correspondencing by Tattoo," in which he recalls meeting Ray Johnson and being introduced to other mail artists at a party. His tattoo of a knife became a topic of conversation that led to friendships with some of the artists and, eventually, to becoming a mail artist.
  Based on written materials and interviews with mail artists and others with knowledge of the subject, Trianfellos' thesis, "A Mail Art Experience" includes an essay about the history, definition and forms of mail art and documentation her mail art project's conception and execution. A note accompanying the thesis thanks Evans for his participation and indicates the project may be expanded.
  A few writings by others are found scattered among the letters (Series 1).
  - By Evans, 1983-circa 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Thesis, "A Mail Art Experience" by Marya Trianfellos (M.A., New York University, 1990), 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
- Subject Files, 1970s-2012; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  Among the periodicals are (Tacit…), an Italian publication titled Bambù, and an issue of New Observations devoted to mail art. Ray Johnson exhibition catalogs dated prior to 1995 and after 2000 are found in the file titled Mail Art Shows and Events.
  Additional art stamps by many artists and a few small periodicals are found scattered throughout the letters (Series 1).
  - Art Stamps, 1980-2006 (Box 6, Folder 9-11)
  - Johnson, Ray - Death and Memorial Tributes, 1995-2000 (Box 6, Folder 12-15)
  - Mail Art Shows and Events, 1970s-2000s; undated; Includes 1 sound cassette; 2 CDs (Box 6, Folder 16-20)
  - Mail Art Shows and Events, 2000s (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Periodicals, undated (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
- Mail Art Projects, 1986-2012; Series 4; 0.8 Linear feet Box 7, OV 8
  John Evans' projects are followed by those of other artists, alphabetized by name of artist. Both volumes of "Fake John Evans Collages" were received in 3-ring binders which were dismantled for better storage. The original order of each volume has been maintained. In addition, announcements of mail art projects initiated by others and stray pieces of mail art from Evans' projects are found scattered among the letters (Series 1).
  Condolence notes to the Evans family are enclosed with several pieces of "Fake John Evans Collages" received soon after his death in 2012.
  - Evans, John, Miscellaneous Mail Art Projects, 1986-1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Behmenburg, Christa, "rats and mice - think twice", 2001 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Caldera, Leslie, Kurt Schwitters: 100 Years of Merz, A celebration of Kurt Schwitters' birth with images by artists from around the world, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Cohen, Ryosuke, "Brain Cell No. 287-No. 300", 1994; Oversized material housed in OV 8 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Kaufmann, Peter W., "World Wide Networkers Congress, 1992", 1993 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Netmail, Angela and Peter, "Congratulations", 2005 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Volume 1: John Evans Fake Collages", 2007-2011 (Box 7, Folder 11-14)
  - "Volume 2: John Evans Fake Collages", 2008-2012 (Box 7, Folder 15-18)
  - "John Evans Fake Collages", 2006-2012 (Box 7, Folder 19-21)
  - Oversized Mail Art Project by Ryosuke Cohen from Box 7 Folder 19, 1994 (Box OV 8)
    from Box 7, folder 19